Guide to the Albert Godfrey Conrad Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Albert Godfrey Conrad papers
1916-1993
MS 1306
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.25
(6 boxes)
The papers consist of office files from the first quarter-century of Albert G. Conrad's career as an instructor of electrical engineering at Yale and an autobiographical memoir. Materials include correspondence, writings, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia, the latter including drawings, blueprints, charts, and a record of a speech by Conrad. The collection is especially rich in materials concerning life at Yale during World War II. The bulk of the papers concerns the Department of Electrical Engineering at Yale, during the chairmanships of Charles F. Scott (1920-1933), Robert E. Doherty (1933-1938), and Samuel W. Dudley (Acting Chairman, 1938-1943), and the beginning of Conrad's tenure as chairman. These papers document the department's administrative and financial affairs, and the research and testing conducted at Dunham Laboratory.
Conrad, Albert Godfrey, 1902-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Accession 1995-M-030 is the gift of W. Jack Cunningham, 1994. Transfer from Engineering and Applied Science Library, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
Student evaluations and grades in box 5 are restricted until January 1, 2018 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Biographical / Historical
Albert Godfrey Conrad was born on May 19, 1902, in Norwalk, Ohio. He received a B.A. degree from Ohio State University for electrical engineering in 1925 and a M.S. degree in 1927. He was an instructor of electrical engineering at Yale University from 1928-1931, an assistant professor from 1931-1940, an associate professor from 1940-1944, and a professor from 1944-1962. Conrad was dean of the College of Engineering, University of California at Santa Barbara, from 1962-1970, and emeritus dean from 1970-. Conrad died on September 13, 1990, in Santa Barbara, California.
Chronology
1902 Born in Norwalk, Ohio, the son of Godfrey and Margaret (Moroney) Conrad
1921-1922 Principal, Gratis High School, Ohio
1922-1924 Instructor, Wheelersburg High School, Ohio
1925 Received Bachelor of Electrical Engineering degree, Ohio State University
1927 Received M.S. degree, Ohio State Univeristy
1927-1928 Worked for General Electric Company, Schenectady, N.Y.
1928-1931 Instructor, electrical engineering, Yale University
1931 Received E.E. degree, Yale University
1931 Married Marion Finch
1931-1940 Assistant professor, electrical engineering, Yale University
1938-1962 Fellow of Timothy Dwight College, Yale University
1940-1944 Associate professor
1943-1962 Chairman, Department of Electrical Engineering, Yale University
1944-1962 Professor
1954 Co-author, Alternating Current Machines
1960 Consulting editor, Encyclopedia of Science and Technology
1962-1970 Dean, College of Engineering, University of California at Santa Barbara
1970- Dean emeritus
Scope and Contents
The Albert G. Conrad Papers consist of office files from the first quarter-century of his career as an instructor of electrical engineering at Yale. The papers have been arranged in a single alphabetical sequence; materials include correspondence, writings, printed matter, photographs and memorabilia, the latter including drawings, blueprints, charts, and a record of a speech by Conrad.
The bulk of the papers concerns the Department of Electrical Engineering at Yale, during the chairmanships of Charles F. Scott (1920-1933), Robert E. Doherty (1933-1938), and Samuel W. Dudley (Acting Chairman, 1938-1943), and the beginning of Conrad's tenure as chairman. These papers document the department's administrative and financial affairs, and the research and testing conducted at Dunham Laboratory. Much of Conrad's own research concerned electro-physiology, and particularly a treatment for athlete's foot involving electrolysis. There are also course materials, including early materials of some of Conrad's older colleagues at Yale, among them Charles F. Scott, Russell G. Warner and Archer E. Knowlton. One folder of material (in box 5), concerning student evaluations and grades, is restricted until 2018.
The collection is especially rich in materials concerning life at Yale during World War II. Conrad was chief of the Timothy Dwight Fire Fighting Squad, and saved a number of materials concerning this group and general air raid drills and defense measures at Yale, including printed matter produced by the New Haven Defense Council. The collection also contains papers concerning courses taught as part of the Engineering Defense Training Program, printed matter concerning student preparation for war service, and papers documenting Conrad's efforts to obtain surplus equipment for Dunham Laboratory after the war.
Other materials in the collection concern electrical engineering professional organizations, the manufacture of Timothy Dwight College paperweights and other artifacts, and the estate of Charles F. Scott. The provenance of the papers is unknown.
For further papers concerning Conrad and the Department of Electrical Engineering during this period, readers should consult the School of Engineering Records, YRG 23, especially Series II, and the Charles Felton Scott Papers, MS #779.
Electrical engineering; Engineering; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States; Educators; Engineers; Conrad, Albert Godfrey, 1902-; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Dept. of Electrical Engineering
- Inventory, 1916-1954; 2 linear feet (5 boxes)
  - Army Air Forces, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, general, 1936, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and papers re:
    - Consulting work and testing, 1929-1934, 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - Research, 1938-1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed matter, micellaneous, 1935-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Scott, Charles Felton, Estate of, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, 1938-1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - War Assets Administration, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Yale Branch, American Institute of Electrical Engineers: exhibitions, 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Yale University
    - General, and student war service, 1936-1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Commencements, 1936-1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Department of Electrical Engineering
      - General, 1932-1943, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Annual Reports, 1931-1942 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Budgets, accounts, 1936-1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Course materials
        - Engineering 10: introduction to engineering, 1934-1942, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
        - E.E. 21: electrical engineering for non-majors, 1916-(1925-1942) (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
        - E.E. 21: electrical engineering for non-majors, 1916-(1925-1942) (Box 3, Folder 21-23)
        - E.E. 22b: principles of radio communications, 1942, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
        - E.E. 39s: electrical engineering testing, 1929-1931, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
        - E.E. 42: alternating current machinery, 1931, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
        - E.E. 43a: alternating current machinery laboratory, 1931, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
        - E.E. 44: electrical engineering practice, 1927-1930, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
        - Electrical metering, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 26)
        - Elecrical metering, for Engineering Defense Training Program, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 27)
        - Inspection trips, 1937-1941 (Box 3, Folder 28)
        - Miscellaneous, 1923-1935, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Course schedules, lists of students, etc., 1926-1943 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Course schedules, lists of students, etc., 1946-1947, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - Lectures, writings, printed matter on electrical engineering and the registration of engineers, 1936-1938, 1941, 1950-51, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - Minutes of departmental meetings, 1933-1942 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Faculty of Arts and Sciences, 1939-1941, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - School of Engineering
      - Committees, 1933-1943, 1954, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - Freshman Counselor, 1937-1940, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - Regulations, miscellaneous, 1931-1933, 1942, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Timothy Dwight College, 1937-1954, undated (Box 4, Folder 38-39)
    - Timothy Dwight Fire Fighting Squad, 1942-1943, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Student evaluations and grades, 1931, 1941-1943, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Student evaluations and grades are restricted until January 1, 2018 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
- Additional Material, Circa 1979-1993; Accession 1995-M-030; 0.25; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Received from: W. Jack Cunningham, 1994 Sep 2
  - Memoir: "As It Was", Circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and additional biographical material, 1980-1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)